If I were going to take down a terrorist
safe [music] house, how would I do that?
Number one, I would want it to be dark.
So, I wrote 0200 at the type at the top
of the paper, 2:00 in the morning.
The team has to be ISI, FBI, CIA.
So, I wrote all that down. We need
[music] battering rams to break down the
door. We need guns, ammunition, night
vision goggles, money, handcuffs. I came
up with a very long list which I ordered
and was delivered to the embassy soon
after. And then a couple of days later,
I got a call from ISI and they said, "We
have a lead. What do you want to do with
it?" And I said, "Ah, I just came up
with this operational plan. Let's get
together." And then at 2:00 in the
morning, we break down the door. Okay.
So, we put our team together and at 2:00
in the morning, we took the battery ram
and we broke down the door of the house.
There were two
al-Qaeda fighters, low-level young
fighters in this house. One from
Tunisia, one from I think he was from
Algeria,
18 years old and 19 years old. They
immediately started crying, both of
them. And one begged us to let him call
his mother. So we put handcuffs. I gave
them to ISI and they took them to a
rubble pindi jail. And I said, "Hey." We
were giving each other high fives. Hey,
that worked. That was great. It was
easy. Then a week later, I got a call
from a friendly Arab intelligence
officer and he said that he had a lead.
He gave me he gave me the address and I
called ISI
and they said, "Okay, let's just do the
same thing again tonight." So, we did.
We broke down the door. This time we
caught two members of Egyptian Islamic
Jihad, very dangerous people.
That worked too. And so we started doing
these, you know, from once a week, then
twice a week, then three or four times a
week, and sometimes two in the same
night. We would have split teams until
the opposite capture in which we did 13
raids simultaneously.
We believed at the time that Abu Zubedo
was the number three in al-Qaeda. He was
not.
He was a he was a bad man. But he was
never the number three in al-Qaeda. In
fact, he had never joined al-Qaeda. He
worked along with al-Qaeda. He created
the House of Martyrs safe house in
Peshawar and he created the two al-Qaeda
training camps in Kandahar and Helma. If
you wanted to get into Afghanistan to
fight, he would get you in. If you
wanted to get out of Afghanistan and go
home, he would get you out. So, he was a
facilitator.
but he was not an al-Qaeda leader. The
second problem that we had with the
intelligence uh on Abu Zuba was we did
not know at the time that he had a
cousin also named Abu Zuba. And so we're
collecting intelligence from all around
the world and we're saying Abu Zuba is
planning an attack in Afghanistan. Abu
Zuba is planning an attack in Jordan.
Abu Zuba was in the United States 2
years ago. Abu Zuba is this. Abu Zubet
is that it's there are two Abu Zubas.
And I remember one of my colleagues
saying, "This guy must be some kind of
terrorist Superman.
If he's all over the world doing these
operations, we can't find him." Well,
it's because there were two of them. We
had very, very specific orders that we
had to take him alive because he was
this terrorist superman and that he
could lead us to Bin Lad. And we caught
him in Fisalabad. And it turned out that
none of the rest of it was true. None of
it. And so I've become very much an
activist over the last 20 years to
release Abu Zubeda and to apologize to
him. I actually met with his attorney
just a week ago.
And the attorney had very good news that
that the American government is in talks
with his attorneys to release him from
uh Guantanamo if we could find a country
that's willing to take him. After I left
the CIA, the uh CIA inspector general
released a report that was written in
2005 that had been declassified. And
that's when the information came out.
And I said, "My god, we risked our lives
for a lie. The whole thing was a lie.
I was ready to die for my country out
there. And it was all based on a lie.
And so I connected with a guard, a
former guard from Guantanamo who
actually guarded Abu Zubeta. And we
wrote a book together called The
Convenient Terrorist Abu Zubeta and the
Weird Wonderland of America's Secret
Wars. [music]
The night that we caught him, after I
specifically said, "Do not shoot him,
a member of the Fiselabad police shot
him three times with an AK-47, no less,
in the thigh, the groin, and the
stomach.
We ended up having to airlift him to uh
Lahore to a military base.
And um I was the only one there at the
hospital with him. And George Tennant
called the director of the CIA and he
told me these were his exact words. He
said 24/7 CIA eyes on which means 24
hours a day, 7 days a week, do not stop
looking at him.
Well, I was already awake for 24 hours
at that point and I was exhausted
[music] and I was afraid I would fall
asleep. So, I tore up a sheet and I tied
him to the bed from his wrists and his
ankles. And then I put the ceiling fan
on high to make it uncomfortably cold so
that I wouldn't fall asleep. And I sat
there like this in a chair at the foot
of his bed. And I just stared at him. He
was bleeding to death. As fast as they
could pump the blood into him, it was
leaking out. And it was on the floor in
a pool. It was all over him. It was all
over the nurses and doctors. It was He
was bleeding to death. It looked like a
like a a scene from a horror movie.
And so after 24 hours, [music] he
finally came out of his coma tied to the
bed like this. And he was looking at me
and I was looking at him and he went
like this for me to come close. So I
went up to him and I moved his oxygen
mask off to the side and I said to
himme, "What is your name?" And he shook
his head like this. So I said it again,
"Shume."
And he said, "In English, I will not
speak to you in God's language."
And I said, "That's okay, Abu Ba. We
know who you are." And he started
crying. And he said, "Please, brother,
kill me. Take the pillow and kill me."
And I said, "Oh, nobody's going to kill
you. we've been looking for you for a
long time. He said, "What's going to
happen to me?" And I said, "Honestly, I
don't know, but I'm going to give you
some advice.
I am the nicest guy that you're going to
meet in this experience.
My colleagues, they're not nice like I
am. So, if there's just one thing that
you do, it's that you have to
cooperate." And he said, "You seem like
a nice man, but you're the enemy." and
I'll never cooperate.
I said, "Suit yourself." I sat with him
for 56 hours
and we talked a lot. He cried a lot. He
said he would never know the touch of a
woman. He would never know the joy of
fatherhood. And I said, "Wait a minute.
You're not the victim here. There were
50,000 people in those towers. What did
you think we were going to do? Did you
think that that we wouldn't try to find
you and and kill you or kill Bin Laden?
You're not the victim. That's why I'm
saying you have to cooperate. We talked
about his family.
He was very close to his mother. Um we
talked about poetry. He wrote very
extensive poetry. He would even write
plays, little one act plays. We talked
about the differences between
Christianity and Islam and and the
similarities between Christianity and
Islam. And finally, I said to him, you
know, I should hate you. I should want
to kill you and I don't I don't. You're
just a man and that's why you should
cooperate. Finally, a CIA jet flew in
and he was very nervous because he
didn't know where he was going and and
we didn't [music] know where he was
going. So, three FBI agents and I
carried him out to the plane. He asked
me to hold his hand. So, I I was holding
the gurnie with one hand and holding him
his hand with my other hand. We
maneuvered him onto the plane. We laid
him across the luggage rack at the back
and we tied him down and he squeezed my
hand and I said I said, "Good luck and
remember, you have to cooperate."
And then I never saw him again.
The entire interrogation program uh at
the CIA uh they called it enhanced
interrogation techniques. I called it a
torture program. The entire program was
a criminal act. This was a a war crime
or a crime against humanity. It's a dark
stain on the modern history of the
United States. And not only was it
morally, ethically, and legally wrong,
it was a failure in that literally no
actionable intelligence was collected
using these torture techniques. The only
actionable intelligence that was ever
collected was collected by the FBI by
sitting across the table from opposite
Var and giving him a cigarette and a cup
of tea and some dates and a pen and
paper to write a letter to his mother.
That's the only way he gave actionable
intelligence. But to beat him and
waterboard him and drown him and try to
shoot him in the head and slam his head
against the wall and put him in a
coffin, none of that worked. [music]